so welcome to voices with verve a key
I'm joined by my good friend
Rafe Kelly some of you have seen Rafe
before on this channel we did the
discussion about building an ecology
practice is something I talk about a lot
theoretically but Rafe is out there
actually playing real time and talent
into making it happen and then I've
posted about a really excellent
discussion in fact via logos that Rafe
and I had had about the hero archetype
and I've been on race channel a lot too
and so it's great that you're here Rafe
so welcome very much thank you very much
John it's a real pleasure to be here
so Rafe tell us I mean I just mentioned
you know tell us a little bit more about
yourself and especially I often hold you
out and I'm proud to do so as an example
are if somebody who's out there building
in ecology practices who's in discussion
with you know good cog saw about this
you know and is you know familiar with
issues around meaning in the meeting
crisis yeah a little bit so you know my
base is parkour and before that martial
arts and really a lot of movement arts
but parkour is where I kind of wind deep
and and where a lot of these things for
to gestate for me but you know I guess
maybe a good place to start is that as I
reached kind of the end of my 20s I had
adopted a very much a kind of a
professional idea of what is archetypal
right like what you should be aimed at
was to be aimed at like the professional
athlete model of being a parkour athlete
and that didn't take me where I needed
to take me and I started getting injured
and had a few other issues with that and
so I started asking this question of
like you know I had I had a competition
that I was training for in 2013 and I I
tore my rotator cuff prepping for the
competition and then I was almost able
to compete I finished third in
qualification but the only way I could
complete when the course is he was to do
this 16 foot running jump where I had to
catch with both my hands and I just knew
my shoulder wouldn't be
able to take it and so I've had a series
of injuries at that point and I kind of
looked in the mirror and I said do you
tape yourself together to try to compete
for a couple more years or do you change
the way that you practice such as it can
be sustainable for life and that really
came down to like why do you do this is
it because of because you're trying to
reach these specific goals or is it
because this does something for you
that's deeply meaningful and I chose
that it was the meaningful thing and and
I had been trying to compete and go you
know and all the competitions were
indoors and I found that what I was
really loving though was playing
outdoors in nature and so I went deep
into that and I was really influenced at
the time by the work of Stuart brown on
play and in in how important play and
unstructured play is and Frank forensic
his work with exuberant animal and so I
was I was I was digesting those ideas
I'm thinking about how they interacted
with what we were seeing with the growth
of parkour and how parkour everyone in
parkour talked about the idea of a
philosophy of parkour but nobody could
articulate what it was and so I started
diving into this and and I really went
deep into play and I started you know
interesting Lee Stuart Browns work talks
a lot about pink steps rats but he
doesn't you know yuck Pink's up in the
research done on the rats but I didn't
recognize it and go back to pang step
directly through Brown wasn't until I
found Jordan Peterson that I was
introduced more deeply into that but I
was researching the rough and tumble
play and and Marc Bekoff and you know my
wife actually did her her master's
thesis on parkour as a form of adult
play so play took me somewhere really
good but there was something about it it
wasn't quite complete because play was
sort of just about the momentary
experience and it wasn't taking you
further than the momentary experience I
see and so I had had all this progress
just from letting go of the structure
that I had had of thinking of being an
athlete right and but then and I was but
then I started kind of falling apart it
was like there was too much structure
which caused stagnation and actually
over stress
then there was too little structure and
it was sort of like I started getting
injured because I just wasn't taking
care of my body enough to do the things
that I wanted to do and it was like my
attention was dissipating across too
many things and so the idea of having
very specific goals came and there was
this interesting thing that happened
I've been teaching you know for many
years and I was teaching these workshops
I was putting all these together these
ideas together and the basic idea is we
evolved from movement and we loved to
move to learn movement through play and
I in in 2016 I found Jordan Peterson's
work well let me back up for a second
what I noticed was when I was teaching I
could I could spout scientific
literature at people as a justification
for why they should adopt the training
things and people respected that but
when I told them stories about my own
experience they were moved by it right
and so I started to think that that
within narrative there was something
incredibly powerful and I wanted to
understand more about it and so in peers
and showed up on Joe Rogan you know
there was the whole political preamble
but somewhere in the middle of the
conversation it switches to being about
narrative and about meaning and that was
when I was like this is this is what I
was looking for right and so I ended up
then layering in all these ideas around
narrative and the other thing that was
happening in parallel to that was I
started teaching these events where I
took people from took people out to the
family property that I'd grown up on and
then we would travel out from there to
to train in these natural spots and and
so we'd have three-day event so before
that all my club teaching was in group
classics and in the group class setting
there's wonderful things that can happen
but there was something completely
different that started happening when
you had three days with somebody and
then we went to five days it was even
deeper and I started listening to my
students and I would ask them at the end
of the seminar like what was what did
you get out of this what was the most
important thing about this and I
expected it to be a jump that they did
right I expected it to be movements that
they learned I expected to be like
knowledge that they attained but they
always talked about feeling deeply
connected feeling connected to a tribe
and feeling all these things and so I
started to pay attention to that and I
was
lucky enough also to have students who
came from the wilderness awareness
school which has been you know this
wonderful place of developing nature
connections it spotting meditative
practices through John Young's work and
so they started coming and they were
initially students
Kyle caulk has been on my podcast
recently was one of them and Jayme mock
and Kyle's really come to work with us
very deeply now but they started
introducing all the nature of connection
practices and thus its bodying and the
tracking and all these things into that
work and seeing how would parallel the
work with with with movement and I also
ran into my friend Simon tackers work
and also mark Walsh who who invited me
and they you know Mark basically said
you're teaching about him and he just
don't know it yet
when Simon had spent ten years in Asia
learning different meditative traditions
and martial arts traditions and then had
the same kind of ancestral approach and
so I got to learn Metta meditation and
and focus meditation from these guys and
see how they were deeply interconnected
to a movement practice so so over time
what we realized was that essentially
there was there was a need to people
word what people were coming to the
events for was because they felt deeply
alienated and disconnected from the
things that give meaning to life and
there was a layer of that that is just
like the momentary experience of the
connection but then there was a layer of
it that is that continued development of
the human being out of its like the
cultivation of the heroic self
so it's like having you know having
goals like I need to be able to lift 500
pounds deadlift 500 pounds it's specific
it's actionable it's realistic it's time
since it or whatever
but why do you really want to do that
right it's not actually motivational in
itself it's just an arbitrary number
it's because it represents this
archetypal sense of the self as being
capable and powerful and you know
whatever it is that you're looking for
and so what I found was that the the
specific smart measurable actual
realistic goals they weren't they
weren't they were too broad enough
umbrella and there was this conflict
between
there's this potential for conflict
between goals and what was actually
deeply motivational and meaningful to
you right right and so then we ended up
thinking okay if we are aimed at the
most heroic development of the self for
a minute self transcendence that's
that's what this should be about and
then we found through the work that
movement has that right parkour was that
was the the genesis around the sense of
self transformation and I was like well
what is what would a philosophy of
parkour look like and then nature
connection practices and then
mindfulness practices and then noticing
that that the community was what people
were really coming for and then seeing
that that there are actually practices
that deepen community and that we don't
have an articulation or respect for them
right so it's like singing songs
together dancing together spending time
in a sauna together doing hard physical
things together right struggle like
hiking for a long time with a bunch of
people all those things foster a deep
sense the bombing that that people are
desperate for and don't have so that's a
bit of the history of how of how this
has all come together and and you know
and then when I found your work you know
the the understanding of how the
connects to embodiment being better than
the environment you know having enacted
right an enacted practice I remember
before I interviewed for you for the
first time I was listening to a podcast
you did I wish I could remember the name
but you said something like the question
that you would have for Jordan is you
know you have you have this proposal of
Christian pragmatism and you have this
this theory and it's beautiful but
where's the practice yes yes and that
that that hit really home with me right
and and and so I've viewed you as this
extraordinary articulator of of the role
of practice and how we bring practice
together at college of practices so I
said a lot and I I don't know if I said
enough but but I want to see what what's
come up whoa
you were very eloquent that was
fantastic yeah I like that and it's
interesting because I sense that there's
this there is this turning and it's
being accelerated by the co vid crisis
towards the the centrality of practices
that have a you know real transformative
power and real aspirational impact and
you know you mean see it on platforms
like rubble wisdom where there a
reorientation toward the centrality a
practice or even maybe practice is it
better because it's a whole network of
practices right it's becoming very clear
and even trying to even in in these
conversations is some of the work I'm
doing with you know with guys sans talk
and Christopher master Pietro and Peter
Lindbergh Jordan Hall right is trying to
turn these conversations into a deep
kind of transformative an aspirational
practice as well so I think that you
know I think I think you put your finger
on something very interesting and I like
the way like well you know I've talked
about this in some ways you know the
work I'm doing is very sort of top-down
you know it's theory and science and I'm
reaching down to try and figure out what
would this look this can practice and in
a very complimentary fashion your
discovery has been very bottom-up you're
in there doing stuff and you and then
you work your way up towards theory and
so there's like this I think this is one
of the ways why we we we we resonate so
well together
because part of the argument I've made
is we need both of those yeah we need
the top-down and the bottom-up and we
need them in to be in into deep and deep
dialogue with each other if we're gonna
afford what you what you said was at the
core of this which is giving people real
transform real transformation in their
meaning of life that has a long-term
trajectory to it I think that's the key
thing and I think what's happening now
with with the Cova crisis is that we're
you know that the the the foregrounding
of the need for meaning as deep and
long-lasting connectedness I think is
coming is just is just being pronounced
precisely because people have lost a lot
of connect
I'm in a certain way and this brings up
a topic that you and I thought we might
discuss which is the idea that that one
of the things that Co vid
crisis is doing is exacerbating the
meaning crisis by inflicting a kind of
Dom aside on the world and this is a
notion that I got from Brian Walsh he
gets him from Fortius and Smith and we
made use of it Chris and Phillip and I
in the in the zombie book and I've been
talking quite a bit about this in some
of the videos and and then you know and
there's been other periods in history
where there's been these kinds of so
dama side is you know the loss of a
sense of home and of course that's
happening with people very much their
sense of where they feel safe where they
feel at home right and and and and sort
of the scope of their identity in the
world is radically shrunk people are
feeling disconnected they're feeling
disconnected of course from a lot of
their loved ones relationships are
ending there's loneliness many people
are describing their experience using
the adjective surreal the sense of
connectedness to reality is disappearing
um and so I think I mean one of the
things I'm trying to do is I'm trying to
I'm doing a lives I'm putting on a live
streaming of the meditation and
contemplation course that I offered will
try and give people some tools and I
wanted to hear your thoughts around
Thomas re and what you think and and
like how your ecology of practices might
be specifically relevant to that issue
is that fair enough
yeah yeah yeah so the this is something
I've been thinking about talking to you
about for a while now this idea of how
does parkour zombies and everything
interrelate with Dom aside I want to
read your book the the story of the
grassy narrows a shinobi I believe yes
was extremely striking to me and you
know he ignited something from a
previous conversation but to summarize
that right there was this this tribe of
people who were living and they had they
had a sense of
far apart their houses should be and
they had a sense of the the meaning in
landscape yeah and they were moved to a
new reservation under good intentions
right because it had access to things
that they thought would improve but then
we saw this massive massive suffering in
their culture right only just a little
bit do you remember it's something like
rates of domestic violence went up right
so the traditional suicide goes up
there's two aspects to it one of course
is a biological physiological we
mentioned this in the book the movement
did subject them probably to some kind
of mercury poisoning yeah but but but
what Brian was work was trying to show
is that the capacity of course is
horrific right and you know in the
Canadian government there's a
responsibility for that and so I'm not
trying to be dismissive and we didn't
try to be dismissive of that in the book
but what Brian was trying to show is yet
but the capacity for the culture to try
and respond and deal with the impact of
this and and sort of deal with with the
movement there them being as you said
moved to a different housing location
was deeply undermined by the fact that
the government had given them a new kind
of arrangement of their their living
space so you've got a culture that these
people are being culture shock they're
being moved ostensibly for good reason
then they're being put under a physical
stressor of your poisoning right and
then what happens is right their ability
to respond to this is dramatic because
they they they they they lose their
sense of home because and this is
Brian's point houses becomes a become
homes when they become basically tools
very complex sets of tools by which we
symbolize inhabit in
act our worldview how we fundamentally
are making sense of who we are what the
world is and and how we relate to each
other and by changing the housing
structure all of these processes of
making sense were massively disrupted so
at the time when these people most
needed to sort of feel really connected
to themselves to the world right they
were suddenly all of this was torn apart
and they and so they get huge increases
in violence and domestic violence and
suicide substance abuse like etc so what
it occurs to me is that a home not a not
the physical structure of a house but a
but a home is where it's kind of like
the central place from which attunement
between the agent in the arena begin to
take disturb the meaning system around
that home then you potentially disturb
that entire agent or inner relationship
yeah and it's relatively invisible it'd
be very easy to say from like that you
know as a white Westerners who's used to
living in a in an apartment block the
the meaning system in widok a
traditional home and the land around it
in the way that it's used is embedded is
very invisible to us and so we can
disturb and destroy something that is
very central to somebody and not even
know that we're doing so Oh totally
totally anyway and we and we also you
know we we also can do it to ourselves
without realizing it
people often when they consider moving
they often are focused on and of course
I'm not saying they should dismiss that
they're focused on the socio-economic
factors and they and they forget I
remember when I like along when I first
moved to Toronto and I was I was hit by
this like there was a look and that was
it was like culture shock it was like
profound culture shock and I I felt you
know sort of a deep anxiety and then you
realize you start doing all these homing
things would they have actually no no
functionality to how you're making use
of your dwelling an associate economic
fashion but what you're doing is you're
trying to make your
you're trying to make your house a home
by doing all this symbolic all the
symbolic work in it to try and alleviate
that weird sense of displacement so I
think we can also like that we I think
it's not only we can be blind to how we
might be affecting other people I think
we're also blind we don't pay enough
attention to how we are affecting
ourselves yeah I mean so this is this is
a little bit far fear but you know I
always am an apology students so this is
something that I've always been
interested in is like culture and
diversity and how these things interact
and and so there's there's kind of two
big narratives that or there's a big
narrative that is dominant academia now
which in many ways is just an inversion
of a previous nerd where the early
narrative was there there is a hierarchy
of culture right and white Western
culture is at the top of that culture
and things is were bite and that
essentially we're trying to get the rest
of the world to catch up all right so
when we impose our culture when we take
the the Native American children you
know here in the northwest we we had
these forced schooling the residential
schools in Canada as well horrible
horrible so we take them out of their
system and you know sometimes people are
being cruel right there's there's
absolutely racism and hatred and all
these things that are involved but even
if it's well intentioned I don't know
what we're disturbing exactly exactly
now so so we see that you know visible
minorities are still suffering in many
ways right and so now if you take the
the old white agency allows everyone to
achieve civilization it's kind of been
reversed and now it's white agency
oppresses everybody right right right
right right right and I think that um
that shouldn't be entirely dismissed
right but I do think that there's
another way that we can look at this
which is along the lines of
cultural change disturbs our meaning
structures and that's disruptive for
everybody and the bigger your the larger
the gap that you're being asked to cross
the harder it's going to be right so in
many ways what you're describing with
the meaning crisis is is the disruption
of the underlying cultural Network oh
yeah everybody's suffering from it but
the people who who the people who've
been on the hockey stick the longest
yeah are suffering the least because
they're better prepared and and so so
like we are the reason that the that a
Native American might be suffering from
dama side is actually the same reason
that so many white kids are committing
suicide yeah it's just that we've got
more cultural technology to help us line
through those waters right right this is
kind of the way that I've been thinking
about that now this is good I want to I
want to unpack this more before we do
but can I just say one more thing okay
yeah this is the thing actually can I
tell you a story of course is I think
that this is this is interesting
so parkour right this is the art that
there was the genesis of this this was a
this was an art that was developed by a
by visible minority kids who are largely
the families of immigrants in immigrant
families in the banlieues of Paris right
so a banlieue is is really a lot like
this grassy narrows thing right these
were these houses these you know France
- the opposite of North America right
instead of turning their city centers
into the housing projects they put the
housing projects on the outskirts of the
cities and so you have these massive
housing developments that are all
brutalist modern architecture that are
absolutely oppressive about people right
and and everyone was packed in there and
this was supposed to be good and
everyone was going to develop because
all of the resources worked were tight
so then you know you have this group of
people from North Africa from West
Africa and from Vietnam mostly who are
all coming into to these bamboos in
Paris so the story of parkour you know
the story of get out of Julie angels
book breaking the jump you can kind of
say it starts one starting point is Jana
Nostra who's his family's from New
Caledonia in Micronesia like a couple
generations ago his family were
headhunters he runs into David Bell
David bells is like he's his father's
Franco Vietnamese and his mother was
French and they're at an arcade and they
almost get into a fistfight there
David's 15 yan is 17 but then the on
realizes that they have a shared friend
and you're all sort of like if you're
afraid if you're friends with my friends
you're my friend so they become friends
but there's this intense thing about
their friendship right they're both
really physical kids right they both
compete in track and in gymnastics and
interested in martial arts and so they
start challenging each other to who can
do a thousand push-ups you know who can
be hit in the stomach who can jump this
and then David's cousins get involved
and then they're a whole little circle
of friends right and so the there's a
proximally nine guys who kind of viewed
as the founders of this there's but
there's more who were involved at some
level but it's glued on
he's West African chose Farah West
African Malik deal West African William
and Xiao Bell who are Vietnamese and Yan
and David and and long who's who's
Italian and French but these guys they
they start doing this right and they
come from like there's abus'd and their
families you know they come from trauma
like david's father was basically raised
by the french military after he was
separated
from his family mm and a lot of the kids
that they grew up with going to be in
gangs going to have all of these you
know be drug addicts you know have all
the dysfunction that is typical of these
communities these immigrant compromise
light communities what you're saying
that I nama saya community right they
came from meaning systems in Africa and
Micronesia in Vietnam that were
disturbed by war by immigration yeah but
it needs these liminal spaces right
there were integrated fully into French
society they were put over there to kind
of be ignored mm-hmm many people went
dysfunctional but these kids they found
somehow if I challenge myself if I if I
burn this energy through through taking
on challenge and if I make overcoming
challenges central to Who I am
that can help me grow so I think this is
a really powerful story and it is and I
was talking to someone who works with
Alaskan native kids and it struck me
that often when people are in this this
place between where they're like it it
can be hot you can be stuck in a place
where the the arrival of guns and sugar
and snowmobiles and whatever has in many
ways made your previous culture
technology kind of obsolete right it's
hard to update too and then you have
this dominant culture over there
but you don't feel fully welcomed in it
either you put in this liminal place yes
very much
look in this liminal place and what's
your identity am i Alaska native or am I
hide or am i you know am i Vietnamese if
I'm not French and it struck me that
that not just parkour but many movement
arts and other practices as well but
they can act as as bridges they're
they're liminal spaces in which you can
have an identity that's shared between
the subculture and the dominant culture
so this this sounds like the argument
I've made that you know when we're in
these liminal spaces and there's lots of
argument right now like Zach Stein is
making
as a whole is in a liminal place right a
lot of people feel that way so sir
reality is an adjective that comes is
prototypical when people are in liminal
spaces individual in it and and
collectively and I've made the argument
that and that serious play is the way in
which we learn is in which we can
appropriately navigate these liminal
spaces yeah and if we used to have of
course places of serious play like
religious institutions but that largely
collapsed for a lot of people and it
sounds to me like the people that you're
talking about the they didn't turn to
religion they turned to something more
primordial in order to reject you Jim
and and and Dragon Ball Z martial arts
movies and in Raymond so the huge myth
which have a huge mythic component to
them of course absolutely
but there's something physical and you
know something that's been interesting
to me as I've as I've explored the space
of meaning and movement is how
appropriate is this marriage right yeah
like am I am I getting outside the scope
of practice of what I should be looking
at but when we look back we see that
very frequently in the past these things
were very tightly interwoven so that
martial arts traditions were developed
by monks yep very much and you know when
you practice Tai Chi you're practicing a
Taoist art yes specifically a Taoist art
or the role of gymnastics in the
Neoplatonic tradition things or sumo
sumo is a Sciuto art right all the
temples had sumo so this this
integration of self transcendence of
spiritual life and a physical expression
is actually I would say quite native to
human beings and I think that um yeah so
I think there's something interesting
there and and and I think there's
something to me there's something very
powerful about the idea of you know if
if parkour can be a bridge for a
immigrant kid to an identity that is
stable
right and meaningful that helps them
resolve this tension between you know
I'm not fully Vietnamese and I'm not
fully French in a positive direction
these movement practices they can be I
think they can be they can be these
identities that help us bridge between
this sense of domicile that we have in
general in our culture that's the thesis
I'm working with there's a good thesis
so maybe I can add to it a bit so right
now you're talking about the
transformation of identity in the agent
but it sounds to me I know you've talked
to me about this before
parkour is also transforming the arena
yes or I mean you mentioned how they're
taking basically there's brutalist dead
end
you know landscape and they're they're
revitalizing it and they're turning it
into an arena that affords them right
all kinds of growth and self
transcendence and connectedness because
you know they're interacting now with
their their environment is now affording
them rather than just containing them
absolutely I mean it's it's very
interesting from a socio-cultural
perspective right because where is
parkour born right kids everywhere all
over the world have jumped off things
have flipped off things have done things
but it sparks into a thing in this one
specific into a like a worldwide
phenomenon right yo levels explode
beyond anything we've ever seen before
and it starts in this brutalist and the
nightmare in a way right I mean every
isn't that terrible but but there's
something of that and that brutalist
architecture it's kind of interesting
right like what this architecture you
know a lot of people like I I think it's
horrible to look at
and it's pretty impressive to be around
all the time and it and it was designed
in a way as like blind to human
aesthetics yeah yeah like our core kids
love it it affords tons of movement yeah
yeah yeah we have a brutalist a Lawrence
Halprin fountain in downtown Seattle
called freeway Park just
blocks of concrete and it's world-famous
right so there's something that's really
interesting about that about this idea
that you know I talked about this I
think in our last podcast but this idea
that III when I first encountered the
the kind of Peter Sounion perspective it
was like odd the breaking the jump like
the process of going out and finding a
jump that's a mini hero's journey for
your your you're looking at the chaos
around you you're finding a piece of
chaos basically and then you're bringing
order to it through overcoming it but it
was only more recently that I saw that
that that that it's actually also the
inverse of that aspect of the hero's
journey because the opposite side of the
of the confrontation with chaos is the
stagnation of order and the need to
bring cast back into the system the the
the waters of life and so what what what
those Park were kids had done was they
hadn't just imagined themselves as the
type of person who can who can confront
something they'd imagined the
environment as suddenly containing all
of these potentials all these anomalies
and we're not previously there yeah yeah
yeah yeah created they created a
entirely new agent arena relationship
reciprocal opening in a very powerful
way very very powerfully yeah and so
they're integrating mind and body
together and then they're reintegrating
right in an enacted imaginal way the
arena and the agent and in getting the
reciprocal opening mm-hmm and then you
have had the idea of taking that and
then situating it in nature as adding an
increased dimension could you unpack
that a bit please
yeah I mean on one level I say I think
that what happened for me is I just was
akin you grew up in nature and was
attracted to it and that I had to stack
these things all right from another
perspective the way that I've looked
well actually let me back up for a
second or part those kids who grew up in
France and started this they trained in
nature and in the city oh I didn't know
that so
yeah if you go to the earliest
interviews with David Bell he says you
know whether in the man-made or the
natural environment and the earliest
videos they feature every and lease
which are families outside Paris but
they also feature source cells which is
a rural area that his cousins lived in
and they feature Fontainebleau
this is kind of a really funny piece of
history but lease and every which are
the birthing grounds of parkour are
about 20 minutes by car from
Fontainebleau which is where the modern
sport of bouldering was developed the
modern sport of what bouldering so
bouldering and parkour are basically
born 20 minutes away from each other
okay
what's bouldering rock climbing so
traditionally of mountaineering and then
mountaineering gives rise to rock
climbing where you're just focused on
going up faces but you do ropes right
then you go big faces and then people
start training to be better at doing
that by just climbing boulders where you
don't have to be roped in
oh wow yeah these kittens all over the
world now where you have rock climbing
holds on walls that are Boulder problems
so the distinction between bouldering
and rock climbing is generally that in
rock climbing you are roped in right
ring you're just you're just finding
these problems so that that separates
out in a lot of ways in Fontainebleau
so anyway so they're there and then in
the in the documentary generation you
know mikaze
I can't remember which one of it is but
one of the other founders she says um
the the body of parkour is born in every
which is urban but the spirit is born of
importance ourselves all right so they
found things that would transfer between
the two and flow with abuse they were
there with both but now an interesting
thing happened when it went hot when it
went international it became very
strongly associated with just the urban
environment Oh what would call it
fervent obstacle course and I think that
part of this may have been that the
earliest popularizers in the UK the
urban free flow group they were called
urban free flow there's a start right
this was the first big group and the
first big website for parkour was urban
free flow and they they did
have a really good understanding of what
was happening with the French guys they
didn't have access to them they couldn't
speak the language there was not a there
was not good you know communication
between these two areas and urban free
flow in a lot of ways modeled parkour as
kind of like skateboarding is very
strongly associated with the urban train
so anyways so is it's not original to me
to take parkour into two nature but the
way that I looked at it was that these
physical capacities that we were
exploring in the city they evolved in
the natural environment these things
because we have we have we have a
heritage as tree climbing animals kind
of a very basic level and I felt that
there was something deeper that we
learned that her that I got when I went
into nature that there was more
information in nature and it was a more
powerful trigger for the flow State
right and then it was kind of there is a
let's say there's I think parkour in
some sense is like a radical reimagining
of the urban world as available for play
like the tree within the building right
yeah I like that that's when you go back
to nature you're actually you're you're
recovering the place where that is
actually more intuitive and more natural
so you're probably tapping into some
deep evolutionary machinery would really
be conducive to getting people feeling
very connected yeah and then then we
find that he naturally brings in that
that curiosity about connection to
nature in a broader way right that a
tree as a living thing it invites a
curiosity about it right that is maybe
different from a building so does that
mean it's easy then I'm trying to get a
sense because unfortunately I have not
been able to come to you've invited me
up for health reasons I haven't been
able to come I hope that changes someday
so I'm getting like people are doing the
parkour and then you have the practice I
forget what you call it where you people
are sitting and they're basically doing
a contemplative practice like on the
natural environment what's it called
again sits
yes we get from from from the John Young
wilderness awareness tradition but it is
a contemplative practice where you learn
to to essentially attend to the
information coming at you from the
landscape so you're really trying to
attune to it very deeply so that would
of course create a sense of
connectedness do you find that it sounds
like these I mean I understand that it
sort of evolved very organically for you
but these are these practices have all
been chosen also it sounds like because
they they sort of like it's eat like
it's easy for people to move from one of
these practices to another they sort of
naturally afford and complement each
other is that is that correct yeah I
mean that's not so much intentional
emergent right it's like I have a base
practice let's say yeah or core and then
parkour in nature and then and then I go
out and I find all these things and then
some of them stick and adhere to that
yeah yeah and and so sit spotting has
been really wonderful and and then also
like I like focus meditation body
scanning meditations and Metta
meditations yeah
romantic contemplations as as adjuncts
to this yeah I can see that and then you
also get like a campfire practice that's
very similar to some of the stuff I'm
trying to do with dialectic and dialogo
so although right now we're doing these
digital campfires instead where you're
getting something like an
intersubjective like you're telling
narrative and and people are literally
circling around a campfire yeah so so
after my encounter soon with with Peter
after my encounter with Peterson's work
at the end of our seminars even then on
retreats well I got the end of this the
first day I would tell one of the Dragon
stories yeah then I would ask people
like why would I tell a story like that
had a memory tree what does this have to
do with like being able to jump or do
vaults and and then
have a discussion about it and you know
I reveal that for me fundamentally the
Dragons story was was a was an archetype
of representation of the hero's journey
and that that that our movement practice
was a way in which we could we could
intentionally go into that and then when
we saw it that way we could start to
generalize the insights from that
process more effectively into the rest
of our life yeah
always the always the intent to
integrate with with your life so it's
supposed to be life transformative it's
not a vacation it's not a retreat in
that sense yeah so let me let me tell
you this degree because I think that's
important like we've talked about this a
little bit before but I think it's
really important you know thinking about
those original guys you know so they
were all training and they were training
intensely and they felt that it was
transforming them right and they were
they were doing just physical stuff
they're doing martial arts but they
started doing these jumps and the jumps
seem to be unique right jumping between
buildings jumping at height and when one
of the guys is considered one of the
founders Williams he's much younger he
was only six years old when this process
started when he's 11 years old he he he
he's kind of training with like the baby
group right there's the older kids and
there's him and he gets to stagger along
sometimes but not all the time and he uh
he sees this jump that the older kids
have done right and he works up to and
he finally does it and it's like this
profound transformation for him and then
he he he asked one of his friends to
come and do it and his friend does it
and as his friend lands it comes down
Williams has the sense that whatever
that jump had meant to him it didn't
have the same impact on his friend and
that that he at 11 he seems to have
realized that that the thing that
mattered wasn't the jump it was the way
that it transformed and so there's a so
there's so what I'm noticed over the
years is that every practice that you
hear people raving about is is a tool
and it's it's a hole right it's it's a
it affords
or it affords or affords transformation
or it affords hiding right so so you can
you can go to a jump because you learn
something and then you take that insight
into your life or once you become
comfortable with the jumps and it feels
like you have that catharsis and a sense
of having overcome something that can
become your place to get that so that
you can avoid facing all the other
places in your life that's important
that's an important difference the
Buddha talked similarly I was talking
about this you know when the classes
about you know people who are using
meditation and contemplative practices
in order to you know pursue awakening
versus those who are trying to hide from
the world and try to become content and
feel like yes very very much I've seen
exactly the same thing in meditation
where where there are there are people
whose meditation practice opens the
world to them just people who's a
meditation practice becomes a place to
avoid the world so I have this slogan I
often use when I'm teaching my students
and I have used it in the in the
meditation class I'm doing online I say
that medic that I say meditation is an
education it is never a vacation yeah
yeah we're trying to bring that so do so
when people are talking around the
campfire I'm just interested does that
mean that they sort of start to reflect
on not the event itself I mean obviously
they're gonna talk about the events of
their day they're human beings
but part of what happening there is that
they're they're reflecting on this
transformative meaning itself and
there's discussion about that does that
come out yeah so the campfire in
practice so so a lot of this thing again
it's it's emergent right no I get it
it's a work in progress but this was
great yeah yeah so you can't you're
camping right you don't know why you're
just camping in some sense so that you
people you have a place to keep people
so that they can then go do stuff they
teach them but it's not part of the
teaching it's just the hanging out after
right that's the way it is so then you
know we go from three days and that's
great and then we go to five days
and the year that we went to five days I
contracted Lyme disease teaching in
Denmark Oh so on the third day of the
seminar I hit the cycle of the Lyme
disease and I was puking and feverish
and all of this stuff oh and we had so I
let I Kyle my the teacher I mentioned he
was a wilderness awareness school
teacher I left him in charge and went
and spent the night at my mom's because
I couldn't camp all right
and that night they played songs we had
we had two couple of East those who were
playing couple Wed up music and then we
had another person who has songs and so
there was this there is this something
had happened when I came back to teach
the next day oh I see and the people
were a tribe in a way that I hadn't
experienced before and it was in deeply
deeply meaningful to them that was in
2016 so the next year we tried to
recapture it and it was still strong but
it was a quite a strong right and so
then we start thinking well what is this
is this is this isn't just this song
thing or this campfire time thing is it
just it's not just a place for me to
give a lecture all right it's not just
it's not just recreation time it's
actually part of the transformation yes
last year we I went did Mark Wallace
commercial friend mark Walsh's he white
key word and he taught me this technique
of having people stop after a certain
period of time training training a
movement practice and have them do a
dialog in practice where they speak for
one minute about what their core
insights were so it's an insight farming
practice right right and so so we
started introducing that and then we
introduced the idea of asking the
students to tell their story and
introducing you know this has happened
over time and and and and the dialogues
that have come out you know we've had
people share some incredibly deep stuff
some traumas that you know people have
never shared outside of that and
incredible incredible conversations and
people people who've come to our
workshop
now they're they're you know they're
staying in contact even though they're
yeah all over the country because
they're they have this this group of
people who they trust and they can
communicate with in a way that very few
people are available to them so you sort
of retooled the I think that's the right
word to use here
you retooled the the campfires to be
sort of you know insight and and
transformation yes metric and that sort
of caught that and that allows you to
recapture what it spontaneously happened
when you were sick is that what you
found yeah
so we so we so we use music so we teach
songs we use storytelling I tell stories
but we also asked the students to tell
stories we did this we did this this
this last retreat that we did for the
first time where we asked the students
to get together in groups and compose a
narrative myth basically I of their
experience at the event and then
presented to the group their insights
from the practice around the campfire
not as much just around the insights
from the data it's kind of summed up at
the end of the day right so we so after
each section we have a sit down and dial
so you have a couple of different
practices that I see and then mention
you also and I've seen a couple of the
videos you also do some lectures and so
and what they play in all of this so the
idea of the lecture is to give the the
philosophical framework right behind it
and the science behind it to justify
them right it's it's like here's your
your justification for the practice and
you give people insight into how they
can continue practicing and then those
also form they form a they form a
foundation for continued dialogues right
right right
so you're providing kind of a what I
often call a conceptual grammar for
people yeah yeah absolutely
so I mean you're my friend so you know I
mean this is a complicated we invented
church like but but but but maybe but
maybe or maybe something you know proto
church that was
you know more present in maybe
hunter-gatherer societies but you you
invented a lot of the machinery of
religion is what I'm trying to say I
mean that's I think that's true and I
also find it uncomfortable I like I know
you do you know I'm not trying to just
make friends well it's it's a funny
thing so you know when we started
parkour like we were all like you know
like my nickname was like the parkour
preacher right yeah he was like it I
could quote David Bell right yeah
David Bell of 2028 right um please does
this and and and it was like a religious
transformation for those of us in the
beginning right it was like something
had come into our lives that have
completely changed us and that was
profound and we wanted to be able to
share it proselytize innocence and but
then there was it was like I think there
are people for whom the movement kind of
self organizes the understanding at
least sufficiently but there's also a
sufficient level of kind of depth when
you're 21 and a different level of depth
that you need as you continue that
process to have it continue to give
meaning to you as you age but but my
business partner was always joking that
we should just rebrand parkour as a
church so that we can get free taxes but
then but then but also I wanted to share
that uh one of our students at at the
retreat you know you know was talking
about how special that retreat was he
was like you know what it brought him
back to his church camp right yeah and
like going out and he tells the story of
basically like a friend I think that one
of their when they went on this long
hike and someone actually sprained their
ankle and they had to carry them back
and then they had to like take them on a
canoe across a lake with like high chop
in the middle of the night to like get
them back and get them treatment now
this was like one of the most
transformative experience of his life
when there's a dirty mural
so in some sense we're really clearing
that and I think that you know what I've
talked about you before is that you know
if you can if you like I've had to
accept that to a degree right that that
the spirituality and and physical
practice can and maybe need to have a
code
a sort of dynamic yeah they're wedded
together they fought each other in
powerful wills and then and then at the
same time I don't want to you know I
tell I tell tell stories that I got from
Peterson and I talk about their
relationship to the Christ archetype but
I always tell people like I'm I'm not
I'm not a devout Christian I'm not
asking you to be to get the meaning out
of this like I think that one of my
favorite things that you say is they had
be able religion without a religion or I
like you to think of as religio yes yes
very much it doesn't mean that you can't
have it right like if you want to if you
if you're a devout Christian you're
welcome if you're a devout Buddhist
you're welcome fueled about Muslim
you're welcome
there's there's machinery within
religion that that is deeply necessary
but my approach to that is definitely I
think it would be the service to what
we're offering if it became too attached
to that well you don't attach it to any
particular religion and all right yeah
like I said I think it's I of course I
was teasing you about to try and poke
you yeah I think it is much more about I
mean you're creating you know you're
creating in these terms I mean seriously
you're creating ritual and mythos for
enhancing religio and I think that's
really really important within an
aspirational program of trying to make
people wiser more connected yeah which
is cool and it's funny because now it
affords me talking to you all right but
I just fell into it right that's the
funny thing about it anyway yeah but I
mean I mean it's funny but it's also it
also it also sorry I don't want to make
this self-serving but it legitimates
or at least provides evidence for an
argument I've been making about a how
how this is fundamental to us and how
this can be built bottom-up it doesn't
have to be belief centric you didn't
come in with this whole metaphysics and
belief structure in order to create a
mythos and a set of rituals that afford
the enhancement of religion and the
transformation of agent arena you just
just emerged and yet it's effective and
it's
powerful yeah yeah it emerged in some
sense despite me well but in a lot of
ways in the beginning of this process I
would describe myself is a very hard
line atheist and yeah extremely
skeptical of religion and and and also
like I always say that I had to be a
little bit of a lone wolf personality
wise in order to go into this place that
nobody else was there
well of course I get that I get that and
snow the the creation of the community
has been so much a self-organization of
the people who've taken on the work
around me yeah yeah just an interesting
yeah that logo so I love that I love
that so I you I mean you did this
spontaneously in a couple of other other
dialogues you know I I now hear you sort
of self described as a non-theist
so there has been a shift for that yeah
I mean you know encountering Peterson's
work was it was really was really
powerful to me and it was quite
confusing because I knew that I was
looking for a narrative but I didn't
understand quite why I was so obsessed
with it and while I was taking my time
away from studying more specific stuff
around physiology and adaption to
exercise and no motor learning and I was
like why am i studying this guy's stuff
so much but but yeah it was profound and
and I I you know I remember when he's
heard the biblical series I told my wife
like I might be a Christian when the
sense yeah but I wasn't you know I'd
love the stories and I love the meaning
and in his per its profoundly shifted
like I just finished Harry Potter with
my daughter right and you know when
Harry sacrifices himself yeah right and
the evil is killed and all that it's
like this is this is an extraordinarily
well done retelling him the Christ
archetype very much and mist on certain
types of Christians
it's a story if I can just interrupt
that's a I remember a story from CS
Lewis a little girl came to him reading
a Narnia Chronicles
and this shows you something about the
depth of CS Lewis and she said she comes
up and she's confessional yes I like
Aslan better than Jesus and he turned to
her and what insight on Swain he said
that's fine that's okay mm-hmm like he
got it that if you know that she was
actually connecting to what really
really mattered above yeah beautiful
yeah I'm actually reading Chronicles of
Narnia now after Harry Potter was again
quite interesting because when I read it
as a kid I had no idea that it was meant
as a direct Christian allegory and I
didn't understand the Christian story
well there's two things there there's
the Christianity but remember what the
what what what is it the professor says
it's all in Plato I don't know what
they're teaching children these days
there was a lot of Platonism running
through that those that's doing a lot of
powerful yeah so you know in one of you
two debates with Peterson you said you
know pragmatism is is parasitic on a on
a objective sense of truth right yes
those lines but I think there's a
there's something profound about the
idea that that that we can't ever know
objectively everything you know we're
always we're always viewing the world
for the salience landscape and in some
sense from a Darwinian perspective all
we ever have is good enough yeah I think
that that struck me as profound and and
that like in the past you know I would
make a parsimony argument for why why
God didn't exist which was basically
that it doesn't it's just an ad-hoc
hypothesis that doesn't add explanatory
power right right but now I think it's a
really weak argument I think it's
commitment abuse of parsimony it's like
these questions are too big for that and
and I don't personally have a sense of
of a divine in the sense that I think a
lot of people talk about God as having
but I do have a very strong sense of the
sacred yes I I would that's clear to me
that's very clear to me and you have a
sense of the shape the sacred that's not
some impotent aesthetic you know
experience you have
sense of the sacred that you share with
others in in that affords them transfer
transformative growth it's a powerful
evocative and provocative sense that you
have yeah tell me what you think about
this if I'm if I'm reading what you're
saying correctly but for me when when
you talk about non-theism it's almost
like the question of the objective
existence of God is just the wrong
question
yes the core of the non-theist position
is rejecting the shared so it checks the
shared presuppositions on both the
theists and the atheists about how to
best understand this phenomena that you
and I are clearly exist which is the
experience of the sacred that is really
transformative of people so right and
what I think is the idea that you know
trying to make trying to frame this in
terms of the existence or nonexistence
of a being and that it's primarily that
and that the way we understand that is
by manipulating beliefs and that we can
sort of nail down get some final answer
about the most appropriate symbols for
that these are all things right and so
the fear says yes to all of those and
the atheist agrees that that's the right
framing and then says no to all of those
and the non-theist says no I reject that
framing that framing is I think actually
miss framing the phenomena and the
meaning that is afforded by that you
know the connectedness that the
phenomena is is is pointing to
so the non-theist yeah rejects that
question the non-theist says can we come
up with framing that puts that well I
want to describe this to you that
affords us to fall deeply in love with
being once again mm-hmm
this is very like that's a Nietzschean
thing almost right it's it's Nietzschean
in some way but I think it's high
daguerreian because I mean I think the
problem I mean this is a critique that
he hiding her made of nature that
Nietzsche basically is still locked into
Nietzsche basically inverts Christianity
so he's still locked to it so I think
the atheist just inverts theism and
they're still locked to it and I want to
break out of it it's kind of like the
the white supremacy versus white
oppression narrative right it's like the
first way that you a narrative that
doesn't serve the first myth first
response to it is just its inverse yes
exactly and you have to try and break
past them which is what you were trying
to talk about with your example of
parkour that neither the white supremacy
or the white oppression model explains
what actually emerged and was created in
that situation yeah by these kids who
yeah you know yeah and you know and they
had agency they created this yeah yeah
and and it and it works it works as a
tool to to bridge right and I think that
um I think that in some ways like it's
you can almost view parkour as a kind of
analogy or a potential precursor to how
can we build these tools that function
it's like I you know God doesn't whether
God exists in a sort of external
metaphysical objective sense it kind of
doesn't matter because the
representation of God or the
meaningfulness of those things has to
exist for us on some level yes um and if
we're not addressing that and if we
can't address it in a way that can light
in the believers and the non-believers
then then we're just stuck with war
right yes yeah but that's what I think
was well that's why I'm so attracted to
your project because you know as much as
I love and respect what Pierson's done
he kind of flirts at the edge of saying
it's neither yeah yeah he rejects the
atheism and he describes Christianity in
such a way that it'd be very easy to be
non-theistic but he doesn't go to the
point of saying I'm actually approaching
this as a non theist
yeah and I as you know I've criticized
him for yeah I'm not doing that because
I think you could make a very clear case
that young is a non-theist for example
so yeah so that onion I've been in I've
been trying to articulate this with this
notion of trans Jack tivity and and the
notion of this is extraordinarily
valuable like that just blew my mind
when I first encounter injectivity there
you know there's the object
there's the observer of the object and
then there's the relationship yeah right
and it's so much of where we get stuck
[Music]
is reframed once you recognize that the
there's a reality within the
relationship yeah well that's exactly
and you know and I think I I bang you
know I've been helped by people like
Corbin and and the imaginal is not the
subjective image or just the objective
thing but as the enacted image schema
that actually allows us to afford you
know a fine transductive you find that
connectedness and I see a lot of like
you I see a lot of what you're doing in
parkour is exactly that kind of enacted
imaginal work imaginal play I should say
yeah so one last question and then we
will wrap it up so a term that I often
use I don't hear you use it as much but
I don't think you're hostile to it
turned agree but but you eat I've felt
it sort of sneaking around the corners I
can you talked about tool and whole
something and this is a you know wisdom
and wave us wisdom fit into this whole
program that you're talking about
there's definitely no sacredness and
spirituality
there's aspiration there's
transformation you know there's you
people have to have to have the you know
they have to have the right insight they
have to discern use this as a tool not
crawl into the hole but like more
explicitly now more focally where what
how does wisdom fit into this for you I
suppose the first response to after that
is I'm a I'm 38 and I jump between trees
like wisdom is such an interesting word
I like I've been insightful for most of
my life I guess
mom tells stories about like going on
walks with me and like finding me
discussing the nature of God with people
when I was four years old yeah yeah yeah
that's clear yeah
and so at 16 I actually the first
religion that I got involved in the only
religion I really been involved in was a
was a Native American sort of recovery I
don't understand right there's a bunch
of of white people following this Native
American leader Johnny Moses doing
something called suus so it's in this
community and and I was talking about my
ideas whatever those ideas were at the
time and a lot of people would tell me
that I was wise right and and it just
stuck in my craw
because how could it 16 you'll be wise I
had no experience for me wisdom was was
experienced married to insight yeah yeah
at a time you know I I love the way that
you've articulated wisdom I don't know
that I mean I don't know that that I've
art that I've have I integrated into the
way that I'm thinking about I'm doing I
want I want to afford people insight
generation yeah is very deeply connect
to that and I think I mean there's the
site one of the things that I ask is do
people do the right it's a neat chink
question right Oh most of morality is
just cowardice yeah I I feel like we
we've lived through the easiest times in
human history and maybe that's ending
yeah but but people most people behave
well in these nice times not because
they have a well cultivated virtue and
wisdom and and ethics but because the
game is set up so that that's what's
rewarded to some degree yeah yeah and
and I think that if you can set the game
up to reward good behavior that's great
but you want to build also the people
such that even when the game shifts when
things change that's still what's
rewarded
and I have this or at least we're
recording I don't see wisdom right I
don't I don't see our political class as
wise I don't see our academic class as
wise and I also see I mean I'm going to
a passion here but I see cowardice
everywhere I see people who who who have
who are not willing to look deeply at
themselves who are not willing to try
hard things who are not willing to take
on difficult questions who who who are
not guys that I want beside me in a
shield wall all right and I think it's
because because they haven't had the
chance to test themselves and to grow
themselves and because our because there
has to be something you know more there
has to be something we're aspiring to
and there has to be systems that give us
that opportunity for serious play but
also a necessity for discipline
right and that that's that's ultimately
what I'm interested in is that that that
that cultivation of virtue through
practice and and one of those is is is
wisdom but I would say that in in the
ecology of of the cultivation of virtue
my role and what my work has been about
is more about courage and your role is
more about wisdom that's fair that's
fair but I I want and I'm very attracted
to the idea of the synthesis but I think
that if I'm a at least at this stage of
my life right if I'm going to do to lead
people on a path I feel like the path
around courage is the path that I'm most
most most informed with right most
resonant with yeah I I feel I have a
subject-matter expertise that I can
fairly put myself in front of people
there and if people get wisdom from what
I'm doing and perhaps they do then
that's great but to take on wisdom as at
the center of it feels presumptuous yeah
fair enough
well I mean we're all swell we are
always and only supposed to be lovely
yes I think that I
love the idea of philosophy oh you know
we were talking about who is the avatar
of the person who comes to the work that
we're doing and it's like it's the
philosophical movement person right yeah
yeah yeah well you and Mark are those
kind of people yeah I think that's very
clear to me that's why no I enjoy so
much spending time with both of you yeah
so that that seems like a good place to
close
Rafe this was really wonderful I really
want to thank you very much for for
coming of course please
I'm gonna sit right now I you know I
think Rafe does really important work
and I always recommending what he's
doing I I hope this video shows you the
depth and the seriousness of what he's
doing and why it's so pertinent and
relevant to the meaning crisis and to
the way in which right now the dama side
aspect is what the meaning crisis is
really being exacerbated in ways that I
think are gonna have some pretty serious
mental health impacts and there are
there's a way there's an alternative way
to go forward we do not have to just
sort of suffer homicide and the mental
health deterioration that comes from
this exacerbation the meaning crisis
there's alternatives we can make use of
and they work and Rafe is here to show
you and to tell you to exemplify the
fact that they do work and so I want to
thank you very much I think what you
what you're doing and and and and what
you've said today is a is good reason
and good evidence for good hope
yeah thank you so much I I'd love to
maybe even have it a second one where we
go deeper into the idea of the Dhamma
side because I think that uh yeah I
think that I think that people still
have not grappled with just how
disruptive this might be yeah um world
that we know I think people are sort of
thinking that they're going to come out
of their bunker and it's gonna be the
same world know after the Great
Depression and World War two these are
the we have to remember that this is
this is the first
world encompassing world challenging
event we've come the analogs are the
Great Depression and World War two and
went Wars pandemics it's we haven't seen
this in 80 years that's right and when
so and after the Great Depression in
World War two we did not go back to the
way things were before those events we
did not go back and I don't think we're
going back either mines team calls this
the awakening from the great nap baby
and especially and I think you agree
with me too that I I strongly suspect
that this is not the only pandemic we're
going to be facing so there's a real
worry about that that if we don't change
factory farming will act markets and a
lot of other things so you know also
melting the permafrost and slashing your
lane for us and ocean currents and air
currents like we're doing a lot we're
messing around with a very very complex
system in a really positive way
absolutely so I think that um if if the
thesis is correct that the that you know
essentially let's say we we had an
identity we had a we had a home to some
degree yeah has been deeply disturbed
and we need bridges to the next home and
to to be able to still start building it
and that means that we can't be those
comfortable people in our shells anymore
we have to have cultivate virtue and we
need those bridges to the cultivation of
virtue and the capacity to create the
next home
well I'll build on the metaphor slightly
I think we had a home but it was it was
actually seriously deteriorated process
so that it's like when the wind is
disturbed it has a very great chance
that it's going to in some significant
way collapse and I think yeah building
bridges is exactly what we need to be
doing right now so so yeah so I offer my
work as a potential bridge for people if
it's if it's interesting if it feels
like it might help them sustain and
cultivate something that will take them
into this potentially a very new world
yeah well we'll definitely talk again
about follow up on this and I really do
think you should get on with talking
about paul van der clay because a bit we
were talking about the the shift in your
spirituality and your attitude towards
God and religion I think he he and his
viewers would find deeply deeply
interesting
well yeah I mean I can pinion maybe you
can send him this yep I'll send him this
and I'll send him an email about this so
thanks again thanks very much
yeah it's always someone immense
pleasure you know I look forward so much
to these conversations me too
I assume you're gonna just and not you
can stop the recording ice oh I'll stop
the recording then what you say I don't
think you did send me a number I think
you're gonna send me a number so that we
could communicate more easily